<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Christians map of the world drawne at the solmne funerals of M. Henry Chitting Esquire, Chester-Herauld at Armes, interred Ianuary 11, Anno Domini 1637. By Edward Sparke Master in Arts, and preacher at St. Mary Islington.</title>
            <author>Sparke, Edward, d. 1692.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1637</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 102 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12696</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23015</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101711</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837519</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837519</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1845</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12696)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1845)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1009:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Christians map of the world drawne at the solmne funerals of M. Henry Chitting Esquire, Chester-Herauld at Armes, interred Ianuary 11, Anno Domini 1637. By Edward Sparke Master in Arts, and preacher at St. Mary Islington.</title>
                  <author>Sparke, Edward, d. 1692.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 46 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I. N[orton] for Richard Thrale,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1637.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Funeral sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1845:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1845:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1845:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1845:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1845:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1845:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CHRISTIANS MAP OF THE WORLD: Drawne at the ſolmne Funerals of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Henry Chitting</hi> Eſquire, Cheſter-Herauld at Armes, interred <hi>Ianuary</hi> 11. <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 1637.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> EDWARD SPARKE Maſter in Arts, and Preacher at S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Mary Iſlington.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Sic pulcherim us olìm. nunc pulcherim a quòndam.</hi>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>skull and crossbones</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <q>
               <hi>Fracta licèt, laetabuntur: The heart of the wiſe is in the houſe of mourning, but the hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of fooles is in the houſe of mirth.</hi> 
               <bibl>Eccleſ 7 6.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by I. N. for RICHARD THRALE. 1637.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:1845:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1845:4"/>
            <head>TO THE UPRIGHT PATRON both of Laws and Learning, the Right Honourable <hi>Thomas</hi> Lord <hi>Coventry,</hi> Baron of <hi>Aylſborough,</hi> Lord Keeper of the great Seale of <hi>England,</hi> and one of his Majeſties moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable Privie Councell: The Felicity of both Worlds.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>GREAT LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe are a Widdowes teares, vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe your wonted eye; Elegies ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torted forth by the ſad Relict of Maſter <hi>Henry Chitting:</hi> I had elſe no purpoſe thus to feed the ſurfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as little deſire as deſert for Printing; And therefore here my penne (as for the moſt part, man) comes into the dangerous World, firſt crying, lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting common frailty in a private loſſe, indeed ſuch blackes beſt ſuit this ſeaſon of
<note n="*" place="margin">Printed in Lent, the Plague not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together ceaſed in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</note> humiliation. For though our bloody waters (thanks bee to God) are
<pb facs="tcp:1845:5"/>well abated, yet ſtill our <hi>Rachel</hi> mournes, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets rod ſtill cryes unto the Citty,
<note place="margin">Micah 6 9.</note> and to the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try alſo; both ſickneſſes of body and ſecurity of minds, call loud enough for cautions of mortality: one, through the wealth and pleaſures of the world, perſwading us of Tabernacles heer; The other by the downefall of many round about us, bidding us build on a more firme foundation. None knowing how ſoone the lot of <hi>Jonah</hi> may fall upon their heads, it becomes us all (like <hi>Abraham</hi>) to be oft ſitting in the dore of our tents <hi>.i. Cogitantes de Egreſſu,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 18.1.</note> thinking of our diſsolution and more permanent proviſion: and in this <hi>Chriſtian-Map</hi> you have the means of both, both worlds delineated, compared, motives and directions for the better choyce. I confeſse, an ordinary, but a needfull ſubject, dreſt like a childe of ſorrow and my buſie charge; plaine and ſerious, without either deſcant or embelliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: Such as it is (with the Authour) is your Honors proſtrate; Importunity brings it
<note n="*" place="margin">Yet not to travell far, but 50. printed, viſits but ſome few friends, whoſe love, J hope, wil cover the Errata.</note> abroad, Gratitude, to your Lordſhip; and theres magnanimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in accepting ſmall things, as well as in conferring great, your Lordſhip both waies known innobled. I am not ignorant how that the graveſt <hi>Pauls</hi> and learned <hi>Gamaliels</hi> of the times ambiat your Noble Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage; enough to argue it preſumption in the younger <hi>Timothys</hi> (to erect ſuch great gates to their little Citties, as your prefixed Name) but that tis knowne as well,
<note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.12.</note> your equall goodneſſe (tutor'd by Saint <hi>Paul</hi>)
<pb facs="tcp:1845:5"/>countenanceth virtue in all ages; and for mine owne part (I confeſſe) of all ill manners I moſt decline in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude:
<note n="*" place="margin">Qui ingratum omaia dixerit.</note> Pardon then well-affected <hi>Zaches</hi> though they clime a little to have a ſight of virtue, ſuffer us engag'd ſpectators, to behold your brightnes, as wel as to enjoy your influence: ſtars loſe not of their height or luſter, for the gazers meaneneſſe; nay, oft have I ſeene an humble Valley grace a ſtately Mountaine: nor will a Deaths-head ſpoyle a Chriſtian feaſt, any more than thoſe old Macedonian Banquets. Yet this I ſerve up here (Right Honorable) not as a <hi>Philips</hi> Monitor (I know your zeale needs no remembrancer) but as the Poets congratulator, <hi>Qui monet ut faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as quod jamfacis, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>ipſe monendo laudat, &amp; h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu comprobat acta ſuo.</hi> Ovid. <hi>Matth.</hi> 27.57.</note> Your exemplary piety, like that noble <hi>Arimathaean</hi> (building the Sepulcher in the Garden) ruminates theſe <hi>Noviſſima,</hi> even in the midſt of earthly happineſſe; and in the throng of all your <hi>ſtately</hi> cares, finds opportunities of retird devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: mongſt which at any time, if a favourable eie but ſecond the encouragement of your gracious eare, theſe Funeralls may haply prove my ſtudies Natali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tialls; and future time give the world better Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of his thankfulnes, who in the mean while, is at his prayers for your Honours, Stocke and Branches, Vine and Olive-plants; that you may all bee happy with the dew of Heaven, and fatneſse of the Earth. Tis the dayly appreciation of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips humble votary and unfeigned Honourer. EDWARD SPARKE.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From your Iſlington <date>Feb. 19. 1637.</date>
                  </hi>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:1845:6"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:1845:6"/>
            <head>THE CHRISTIANS MAP OF THE WORLD: Drawne at the ſolemne Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neralls of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Henry Chitting</hi> Eſquire, Cheſter-Herauld at Armes, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Ian.</hi> 11. <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1637.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>MNIS dies, omnis, hora quam nihil ſumus oſteudit, &amp;c.</hi> Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day, you ſee, nay, every houre (ſaies <hi>Seneca</hi>) ſhewes us what a Nothing wee are,
<note place="margin">Libro d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> brev. vitae.</note> and by ſome freſh argument or other puts us in minde of our forgot mortality: had not each <hi>Day enough of its owne griefe,</hi> this could ſupply the reſt,
<note place="margin">The occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Preface.</note> we could now lend our neighbours teares, but that (I feare) com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon calamities have already ſtord them; ſtord them with ſuch ſad ſpectacles as lieth before us: ſuch indeed for fraileneſſe, but ſeldome (I thinke) ſuch for goodneſſe: one thats Text enough for a diſcourſe,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 20 7.</note> were it as long as Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> Sermon, <hi>Act.</hi> 20. but that, here, double modeſty prohibits Panegyricks;
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:1845:7"/>and you know funerall Sermons are not ſo much to glorifie the dead, as edifie the living: and therefore wee will take another Text, wherof yet Hee ſhall be the Comment, while wee the Applicatours: and that is written in the thirteenth Chapter of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> and the fourteenth verſe.</p>
            <q>Wee have heer no continuing Citty,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Text. Heb.</hi> 13. <hi>verſe</hi> 14.</note> but wee ſeeke (or looke for) one to come.</q>
            <p>THat Wiſe obſerver of a Time for all things <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 3.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 3.</note> tells us of a <hi>tempus naſcendi,</hi> a time to be borne, and <hi>tempus moriendi,</hi> of a time to die, but not ſo much as mentioneth <hi>tempus vivendi,</hi> any time at all to live; Man having indeed to certainty of that, but paſſing from his proper to the common Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (from the grave of the wombe, to the wombe of the grave) as ſwift as either ſhip or ſhuttle, winde or arrow; like
<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 9.25.</note> 
               <hi>Iobs</hi> Poaſt, having ever one Citty to leave, an other to make toward, none to abide in, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>&amp;c. For wee have heere no continuing Citty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ere we enter this ſame City, let us look a little on the gate of it, this word
<note n="b" place="margin">The context in the particle For.</note> 
               <hi>For:</hi> 't will bring us better acquainted with the context, and, as a Porter open to us the dores of this building. It is <hi>particula rationalis,</hi> ſay the Schooles: <hi>For,</hi> is commonly a relative parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, whereſoere prefixt, ſpeaking thoſe words a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of precedent matter: and ſo indeed tis heere; Saint
<note n="c" place="margin">Vide Parei praefa in Coment ſuper Hebraeos.</note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> now taking his farewel of the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> (as I may make him the Author with more Seconds
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:1845:7"/>than opponents.) The Apoſtle, I ſay, in this laſt chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of his Epiſtle, legacieth many pious duties to their practice (enforcing all his documents with reaſons.)</p>
            <p>As in the firſt place
<note n="d" place="margin">Hoſpitality. verſ. 2.</note> Hoſpitality, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. verſe. 2. <hi>bee not forgetfull to lodge ſtrangers</hi> (ſaies hee) For <hi>thereby ſome have entertained An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next loyalty in
<note n="e" place="margin">Chaſtity. v. 4</note> wedlocke, inviolation of the nuptiall bed, verſ. 4. <hi>Marriage is honourable, &amp;c. but whoremongers and adulterers God will iudge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly,
<note n="f" place="margin">Content v 5</note> contentedneſſe with any eſtate, verſ. 5. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>be content with thoſe things that you have,</hi> For <hi>God hath ſaid it, I wil never leave thee nor for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly,
<note n="g" place="margin">Conſtancy. verſe 9.</note> perſeverance in religion, v. 9 <hi>be not car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried about with divers and ſtrange doctrines</hi> (ſaies hee) For <hi>tis a good thing the heart be ſtabliſhed with grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly,
<note n="h" place="margin">Patience. v. 13</note> patience and humility in the 13. verſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Let us goe forth out of the campe bearing his reproach, for wee have here, &amp;c.</hi> As much as if he had ſaid, Chriſt (like that ſin-offering burnt without the campe,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Levit.</hi> 6 36.</note> 
               <hi>Lev.</hi> 6) ſuffred without the gate (.i.) moſt ignominiouſly for place and manner; let not us Chriſtians therefore wanton out our lives in Tents of pleaſure, but follow ſuch a Maſter out of the City (.i.) <hi>converſationem mundi exeamus:</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Ecolampadius in locum.</note> relinquiſh we our carnal converſation, not faſhioning our ſelves according to this world; a world that aſcertaines us of nothing but of our uncertainty, a <hi>non habemus, here no continuing City:</hi> tis fit then wee thinke of an abode elſewhere, it becomes diſcarded
<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 16 8.</note> Stewards to provide them, each imitate that wiſe one in the Goſpell, purchaſe you a perpetuity,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> either by ſuch do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good, or patient ſuffering ill (no matter w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> way
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:1845:8"/>God bring us to Heaven) and come the worſt, wee know Chriſts Thornes were platted into a Crowne, that
<note n="l" place="margin">2 <hi>Tim</hi> 2 12.</note> 
               <hi>if wee ſuffer we ſhall alſo raigne with him.</hi> Let the world build on ſand, while hee is our Rocke wee cannot want an houſe ſhall ſtand eternall in the Heavens, <hi>a City, whoſe Builder and Maker is God:</hi> and this is it we looke for, That we long for <hi>futuram expectamus:
<note place="margin">Text.</note> Text.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But becauſe ſorrow, I know, is a paſſion loves no prefacing, I will forthwith ſpread my mantle and divide theſe waters; and then heeres at one ſide, <hi>Mundi indigentia,</hi> Earths inhoſpitality, <hi>Non habemus, here no continuing City:</hi> at the other, <hi>Coeli ſufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia,</hi> Heavens all-ſufficiency, <hi>futuram expectamus, wee looke for one.</hi> Which two parts, I may expreſſe, as
<note n="m" place="margin">Zeno.</note> the Philoſopher of old his two Sciences Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick and Logick: the world appeares here <hi>pugna con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractâ,</hi> as with a clinched fiſt, readier to give a blow than a benefit, a very withered <hi>Icroboam,</hi> whoſe hand is ſhortned that it cannot helpe, not helpe us to a continuing Citty, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>here wee have none.</hi> But the tother is <hi>Manus Expanſa,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Diviſion.</note> the open hand of Heaven, fuller of aſſiſtances and bleſſings, than all Rhetorick can delineat, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Indeed this Text is the <hi>Chriſtians Map of the World;</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting likewiſe of that
<note n="n" place="margin">The paire of Globes, Coele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiall and Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtriall.</note> paire of Globes Coeleſtiall and Terreſtriall: Globes (I ſay) not Coſmogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phicall, but Theologicall; one of them not ſo much diſcovering the rarities of Earth, and flouriſhing Cities of the world, as demonſtrating the vanity and emptineſſe thereof, and that there is no continuing City in it: The tother not ſo much teaching us the motion of the Starres, and walking unto Heaven with a ſtaffe, as how wee may one
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:1845:8"/>day ſhine among thoſe Lights, and really inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit that ſame glorious City, which is ſome Happineſſe heere, but to hope for <hi>Futuram Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectamus, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt of theſe (mee thinkes) the
<note n="o" place="margin">The Terre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriall Globe of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Map. <hi>Matth.</hi> 4.</note> lower Globe, deales with us heere, ſomewhat like Satan with our Saviour, <hi>Matthew</hi> 4. Setting us, as on a Pinnacle of the Temple, ſhewes us all a faire Proſpect of the Earth; yet with a true, not his falſe glaſſe; not as a lure, but as a caution, not in the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of the Tempter, telling us of Kingdomes and the glory thereof, but in the Apoſtles, <hi>Tranſit Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus.</hi> 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 2. <hi>The world paſſeth, and the glory thereof;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.17.</note> paſſeth! I, and muſt one day in the
<note n="p" place="margin">Partes imitan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur Naturam totius.</note> totall paſſe to nothing, as now in the parts, to <hi>no continuing City:</hi> which defect and indigence of the world, reſults apparantly from theſe three circumſtances of the Text: <hi>Quis, Quid, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Subdiviſion. in</hi> 3. <hi>circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances.</hi>
               </note> the Plaintifes heere con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doling, <hi>wee: wee,</hi> the generall race of <hi>Adam, wee,</hi> mortalls, becauſe <hi>wee</hi> ſinners. Secondly, their wants, what they are ſcanted of, and thats a place of reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, <hi>a continuing City, Non habemus, we have none.</hi> Laſtly, the Scene of all theſe miſeries, where we are thus ſtreightned, and thats <hi>Hic</hi> here, in this ſame dirty
<note n="q" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> priſon Earth. <hi>(Text)</hi> Briefly of them, and with a diſcourſe as fitting as the ſubject, <hi>no continuing City:</hi> and firſt of the Plaintifes <hi>Wee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what? have wee no continuing City?
<note place="margin">Firſt circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, <hi>Quis.</hi>
               </note> by your favour (holy Apoſtle) did not the Creatour, ſo ſoone as hee had built this great houſe the world, and furniſht it, bring in Man his Tenant there, and ſole poſſeſſour? can we complaine of wants? did not all creatures then weare mans livery, a name of
<pb facs="tcp:1845:9"/>ſervitude, and the very wheeles of Time it ſelfe,
<note n="r" place="margin">A reflection on mans Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation and his fall.</note> appointed to attend him unto immortality? Can they then, whoſe is the whole Earth, want Cities? whoſe Chariot, Immortality; whoſe Lackquie, Time was; can they want continuance? is heere a <hi>non habemus? we no continuance heer!</hi> Indeed the World was thus mans Royall-Mannour once (all Creatures holding of him) Paradice to have beene his <hi>Continuing City;</hi> and all this too, leaſed out to him (paying but the Rent, Obedience) for as many lives as hee ſhould have Poſterity: But the edge of his ambition cut off this entay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Happineſſe, hee would bee Paramount, Chiefe Land-lord, He: ſo breaking the conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, forfeited his everlaſting Tenure: that now hee is but a Tenant at will to an offended Land-lord, and ſcarce an equall ſharer in the vivacity of his brother-animals; but this miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and mortality of Man, is a condition not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed in him by God, who (as Hee is Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe Immortall) had put a Coale, a Beame of Immortality into ûs, which wee might have blowne into a Flame, but blew it out by our firſt ſinne; wee beggered our ſelves by heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning after falſe Riches, and therefore now are driven to our wants, to theſe complaints <hi>Non habemus.</hi> Wee infatuated our ſelves by liſtning after falſe Knowledge: I, that Tree of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge bereft us of the Tree of Life, taught us to know evill onely: and left us doubly <hi>like the beasts that periſh.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 49.12.</note> Pſalme</hi> 49. both for infatuation and corruption: like the beaſts indeed for praecipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation unto death, but not for the protraction of their life; moſt of them running man out of breath
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:1845:9"/>if wee may beleeve the
<note n="ſ" place="margin">Virgilii Epigr. de aetat. animal.</note> Naturaliſts (as ſpecially, I thinke in this particular) the Crow nine times numbring out his age, the Stagg foure times excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding hers, the Raven againe trebling his, the <hi>Phoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nix</hi> as long liv'd as all of them. Theſe and others ſport and chant away whole centuries of yeares, while man ſits ſighing over his poore handfull,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalme</hi> 39 5.</note> 
               <hi>Dies feciſti palmares meos. Pſal.</hi> 39. <hi>Thou hast made my daies but a ſpanne long,</hi> nay rather a ſhort ſpanne; <hi>Mine age is nothing unto thee,</hi> ſaies <hi>David,</hi> there to God, that might ſay heere unto the beaſts, mine age is nothing unto theſe. And yet it would favour but of learned Heatheniſme,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> to chide at Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture (as ſome have done) and call her Step-mother to man, and naturall to others; the
<note n="u" place="margin">Ariſtot. in Hiſtor. Anim.</note> Philoſopher himſelfe takes of that cavill, affirming one day of a life of reaſon, above an age of non-intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, beyond all their longaevity of ſenfe: but Divinity turnes this ſeeming diſcontent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a comfort, informing us that this life pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly belongs to things of ſenſe, all its chiefe blandiſhments (treaſure or pleaſure) being but ſenſuall, and no otherwiſe than imaginarily good,
<note n="x" place="margin">The good man envies not the bruites vivacity.</note> much good may it doe them, then with the length of this life, that are to have none other, <hi>Non equidem invideo:</hi> while nobler ſoules of reaſon and religion, trampling on this, haſten to a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; a life among their Brother-Angels, in their owne Country, Heaven; There to meaſure reall felicities no more by Time but by eternity.</p>
            <p>No longer then let this bee a complaint but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, <hi>non habemus,</hi> that wee have heere <hi>no conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing City.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:1845:10"/>
            <p>Thus having brought you acquainted with the Plainteifs (as wêll as with your ſelves) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider now their wants,
<note place="margin">Tranſition to the ſecond particle.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>we have not a continuing City.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A continuing City</hi>] Wee are not heere reſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned unto the Letter, as ſpoken of materiall buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings (though even in that ſenſe alſo it bee true e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough) <hi>Mors etiam ſaxis, obeunt &amp; Marmora.</hi> Citties have their period and diſſolution,
<note place="margin">The litterall truth of the Text.</note> both oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſionall and naturall. Some of them, like goodly <hi>Troy,</hi> and better <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> thoſe Phoenix-Cities of the world (in ſucceſsive Ages) buried in fiery Tombes, rak'd in their owne Aſhes: Others, too many of them (witneſſe all <hi>Germany</hi>) like old <hi>Roome</hi> and <hi>Carthage,</hi> ſackt and demoliſht by the bloody hand of Warre; ſo that (you ſee) the Emperiall Cities of the foure great Monarchies, nay, thoſe Monarchies themſelves, all as well as
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſai.</hi> 47.1.</note> 
               <hi>Babylon,</hi> now ſit in the duſt: and 'twas but flattery in that
<note n="*" place="margin">Livius.</note> Hiſtorian, who called <hi>Rome, Eterna Civitas,</hi> after ſo many downefalls, and ſcarce a feather now of that proud Eagle left: it was not altogether a ficti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Poets deſcribing of old <hi>Saturne,</hi> their god of Time, how hee devoured his children, though of ſtone, (for ſuch they feigned hee had) I am ſure the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is reall, and calls him <hi>Tempus edax;</hi> for whatſoere Time brings forth, Time deſtroyes: This I need ſay no more of, every languiſhing bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, every nodding ſtructure is a demonſtration; and had not pious care, and ſuddaine too, prevented, that publick-glory of the Mother City, Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> Church had preacht a <hi>non permanentem,</hi> the litterall truth of the Text, but happy are they who build
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:1845:10"/>ſuch Tabernacles heer, that are not chid by that ſame Prophet <hi>Haggai.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Haggai.</hi> 1 4.</note> 1 <hi>Is this a time for you to dwell in ſeiled houſes and let mine Houſe lye waste, &amp;c.</hi> Yet alas how wanton now a daies is the worlds invention for ſuperfluous building, Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples are to old faſhion'd, the zealous
<note n="y" place="margin">Bernard.</note> Father may ſtill ſigh. Men build as though they ſhould conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue for ever, and glut as though to dye to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, which indeed they may rather feare,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſai.</hi> 5.8.</note> ſuch a woe being denounced againſt them. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5. but to avert it, imitate that eccleſiaſticall Centurion,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 7.5. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Chryſoſt. hom.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>Luk.</hi> 7. and, if thou needs wilt build, let Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> be a little thy ſurveighour; Wouldſt thou erect beauteous and ſplendid Edifices? I for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid thee not (ſaith hee) yet found them not on earth, tis but an heape of ſand, but ſituate in thoſe calme Regions that are above the breath of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, build in Heaven <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Heere lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, <hi>no continuing City:</hi> Beſides, too many now a daies (God knowes) finde another ſenſe to ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie the Text, by reaſon of their tradeleſſe ſhops and fickle offices, experience it a failing a diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing City: but wee ſticke not on the barke any longer,
<note place="margin">Adouble ſynecdoche.</note> led further than the letter by a double ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>necdoche. Firſt, <hi>Continentis pro Contento,</hi> Cities heere put for the inhabitants, and our want of peacefull reſidence, ſhadowed under their diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance (the Text) ſtrongly reflecting on that pilgrimage of <hi>Abraham. Gen.</hi> 12.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 12. City for the inhabitants. <hi>Gen.</hi> 23 18.</note> where hee is called from his owne Country and his Fathers houſe, to divide a life between variety of ſtrange lands and dangers; ſo that indeed wee reade of none other ſetled poſſeſſion that he had but <hi>Mack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelah,</hi> his onely purchaſe a place of buriall, thus
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:1845:11"/>it was with the Father of the Faithfull, <hi>he had no continuing City:</hi> Nor any thing better with the children: few and evill have beene the dayes of my Pilgrimage (ſaies old <hi>Iſrael Gen.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chap</hi> 49.</note> 49.) long and evill the daies of our Pilgrimage, murmure the children of Iſrael in the wilderneſſe: <hi>Exo.</hi> 14. That Iourney,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod</hi> 14.</note> a true Type of the Saints way to Heaven, <hi>per varios caſus,</hi> &amp;c. who wandred up and downe (ſaith hee) deſtitute and afflicted, <hi>Heb.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.37.</note> 11. Militant is the Churches name, ſhee is an hoaſt upon continuall marches and removes; Our habitations heere, ſo often varied by occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, either of ſome loſſe, diſ-favour, ſickneſſe, or of death (I need give no examples) that, like the traveling Common-wealth of Iſrael, wee have rather ſo many-ſeverall ſtations, than appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priate manſions: <hi>Non habemus hîc permanen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe,
<note place="margin">Synec doche partis.</note> heeres a Synechdoche Partis, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by this word <hi>City,</hi> as the prime part and Maſter-peice of Earths perfection, is put for the whole glory and happineſſe thereof: and ſo a <hi>City</hi> is an emblem of Strength, of Unity, of Reſt, of Safety: in neither of which reſpects (as Ile ſuccinctly ſhew you) have wee <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> heere any <hi>Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing City.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 10.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 60.9.</note> tis an emblem of ſtrength, <hi>Prov.</hi> 10. <hi>The Rich mans wealth is his strong City:</hi> and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 60. <hi>Who will lead me into the ſtrong City?</hi> This is the frequent Epithite, through the holy booke, ſtrong and well fenced <hi>Cities:</hi> indeed theres the <hi>Vis <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nita,</hi> the combination of moſt Men and Armes, the Store-houſe of Munition, <hi>Civitas cor reipub:</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:1845:11"/>Tis the heart of the body-publick,
<note place="margin">A City an em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleme of ſtrength. Man <hi>no conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing City.</hi>
               </note> the ſeat of moſt ſpirit and vigour, deſervedly may theſe be called ſtrong houlds: Now what a <hi>City</hi> man hath in this ſenſe, ſoone bee your owne Iudges: walke but about it, view well the Towers thereof (if you can finde any) how weakely is hee fenc'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with theſe thinne walls of clay! walls, that every Ague ſhakes, every Dropſie drownes, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Feaver fires, every Danger batters; one Fort indeed theres in it, the heart, but that ſo feeble, as tis in a continuall trembling, a palpitation not more for breath than trouble, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 38.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm</hi> 38.10.</note> watchmen too it hath, eyes placed in a Tower, the Head, but neither foreſeeing or preventing miſchiefe; at beſt exerciſes, either dimme or drowſie. The Souldiers of it, the Hands, oft treacherous, advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taging the Enemy, and by ſinnes wounding his owne Boſome, while in all this extremity his Carriages the Feet are unable to convey him from ſurpriſall, or keepe him from being captive to the grave: ſo weake a <hi>City</hi> man is, that even wormes doe conquer it
<note n="*" place="margin">Plinius Nat. Hiſt.</note> 
               <hi>Pliny</hi> tells us, for a wonder, of a City undermined by Conies; but wormes tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph ore this, and ſcarce ere glory of the victory. What is it trow, Philoſophers call Man a little world for? is it becauſe hee hath ſuch Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes in him, ſo many Cholicks and Palſies? is it becauſe he hath ſuch Thundrings, ſuddaine Noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in his Head? becauſe ſuch Lightnings, Inflam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations in his veines? Hee is a little world in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, himſelfe the earth, and his miſery the ſea: nay,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> a great world of weakneſſes (God knowes) borne the moſt helpeleſſe of all creatures, and lives the ſport of every leaſt diſtemper: how ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:1845:12"/>here for man is Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.29.</note> 11. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>who is weak, and I am not weake:</hi> yet put the caſe (with <hi>David</hi>) hee bee ſo ſtrong, hee come to eighty yeares, yet is it no <hi>continuing City,</hi> but a doubled miſery, <hi>labour and ſorrow:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal</hi> 90.10.</note> Pſal.</hi> 90. <hi>non habemus, we have heer no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing City, no City of strength.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly,
<note place="margin">A City a figure of unity. Man <hi>no continuing City. Pſal</hi> 122 3.</note> a City is a figure of unity. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 122 <hi>Ieruſalem is as a City that is at unity with it ſelfe:</hi> at unity, I, a City like each building of it is an aggre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of many into one, the proper place of lawes and government, which are the cauſes and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainers of peace, unity and concord. But alas! wee have no ſuch City, <hi>no continuing unity,</hi> but rather heer, continuall diſcord, witneſſe too many unqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et Families, our clamorous ſtreets, and the reven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging Hall: indeed, ſo deepe root hath that envious mans ſeed taken in the ground of humane hearts, that the whole world almoſt (would I could ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt either Church or State) is become little better than a field of Tares; for the firſt, what flouds, what Seas can lend us teares enough to bewayle this want of unity in matters of Religion? how is the ſeameleſſe Coat of our bleſſed Lord now a dayes,
<note place="margin">Want of unity in the Church.</note> rent and torne by factious noveliſts, which the bloody Souldiers themſelves ſpared, that it might prefigure his united Church? how is the Spouſe like her Head and Saviour, crucified be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene two malefactors! at one ſide the inſulting Papiſt, at tother the murmuring Praeciſian! while I ſpeake of love, I will not ſtrait wiſh both cut off that trouble us, but as our charitable mother-Church hath taught us, pray, <hi>Lord forgive our E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, perſecutors and ſlanderers, and turne their
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:1845:12"/>hearts;</hi> for Religion hath no ſuch ſcandall as this want of union: And for the Common-wealth, how full of jarres and contentions?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rigida pugna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>han Calid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> Ovid. Met 1.</note> The Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, fire and water not at ſuch ſtrife as men, ſure that Prophet ſpake of our times, <hi>Ephraim against Manaſſeh, Manaſſeh againſt Ephraim, and both againſt Iuda. Iſai.</hi> 9.21.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſai</hi> 9.21.</note> all ſo captious of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignities, ſo apprehenſive of all treſpaſſes, ſuch going to law for trivialls;
<note place="margin">Hiſtor.</note> that what was anciently ſaid of the fryars of this Realm (with a little varia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) may be ſaid of the Lawyers, Thoſe liv'd of the Ignorance, but theſe wax fat on the ſtrife of the people: ah, what is become of that ſinne-covering Amity? the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and badge of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Chriſtianity!
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 50. <hi>Ecc. Hiſt.</hi>
               </note> as <hi>Euſebius</hi> told a Biſhop of his age, that askt him, how he ſhould know the Chriſtians from the Infidels, in thoſe miſcellane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous times, <hi>Vide quam invicèm diligunt Christiani,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>O foelix homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num genus, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtros animos a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r, quo Coelum regitur, regat: B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>et lib.</hi> 2. <hi>con. Iohn</hi> 13.35.</note> obſerve but how they love each other, how faſt thoſe brethren hold the bands of Amity: and the ſame diſtinction gives the Biſhop of our ſoules: <hi>Heereby I know that you are my Diſciples, if you love one another. John</hi> 13. But how are wee degenerated into Nabaliſme? love fled, and not ſo much as friendſhip left: very Heathens and Jewes had both their <hi>Amicorum paria,</hi> their golden paire of friends; as <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Ionathan</hi> whoſe ſoules were knit together: <hi>Theſeus</hi> and <hi>Perithous,</hi> who durſt exchange their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomes, and bee the mutuall ſewers of their flowing Hearts. But hard it is among Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians now to finde ſuch Unity (as the Apoſtle ſayes) I ſpeake this to our ſhame; Now love ſits on the lips, and can ſoone take her flight,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:1845:13"/>frothy Courtſhip,
<note place="margin">Humane friendſhip fraile.</note> 
               <hi>Iudas</hi> kiſſes, <hi>Ehuds</hi> embrace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are the friendſhips of this age; or if any be more real, yet are they oft leavened with incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy, and like the leagues of warre, hold but for their owne hopes and ends; very Mary-golds that follow but the Sunne, and cloze againſt the clouded Evening: Now for the <hi>Cor neſcium to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merare fidem!</hi> that Heaven-borne ſpirit that dares bee faithfull, in ſpight of all the ſhuffles the rude world puts on him, <hi>dic muſa virum,</hi> that knowes not upon any urgencies to violate devoted friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip (yet to keepe words, is a qualification of a Saint,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal</hi> 15.4. <hi>Prov.</hi> 31.10.</note> 
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15.) but ſuch an one, were as great a rarity as <hi>Salomons. Prov.</hi> 31. nay the Text con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes it an impoſſibility, <hi>non habemus, we have here no continuing City, no City of unity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly,
<note place="margin">A City an em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blem of ſafety. Man <hi>no conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing City.</hi>
               </note> a City is an Emblem of ſafety, of ſafety by conſequence, as before of ſtrength, indeed our ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is by Defence, That by ſtrength, &amp; both by ſuch well-fenced Cities (as inſtrumentall meanes:) in the 35 of Numbers you read of Cities of Refuge,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Numb.</hi> 35.6.</note> Cities where very Delinquents might find ſafety: But wee haue none ſuch heer, to ſecure vs, euen from undeſerved Dangers (undeſerved I mean par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly by any ſuch notorious crime) no, of all the Fortifications in the world, I would faine ſee that Place, that could wall out a Famine, or a Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, I'me ſure Samaria was a well-fenced City, and yet both theſe enterd it and wellnigh vnpeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled it.
<note place="margin">1 <hi>King.</hi> 18.</note> 1 Kings 18. nor need wee goe ſo farr for ſad Examples. They haue lately enterd our own Cities, one keeping ſtill Poſſeſsion, no Fences heer are Iudgm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t-proofe, not Argob's Cities, let them
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:1845:13"/>bee wald as high as heaven, Deut. 3.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dent</hi> 3.5.</note> a ſhowre of vengeance,
<note place="margin">Saloimus.</note> Hell out of heauen ſhall raine down on Sodome, be it nere ſo well immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſh</hi> 6.20.</note> and indeed who dares put Confidence in a City-walls that hath but euer read or heard of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rico. An Arme of fleſh is but a bruiſed Reed, no Safety either in Horſes or Chariotts; Pharaoh found one of them (as Dauid ſaies) a vaine thing to ſaue him, Exodus 14.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod</hi> 14.25.</note> where his Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riotts hurried the faſter to deſtruction for their wheels being off, and what ſafety in the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of an Hoaſt Zenacherib will tell you, whoſe Confidence was as great as his Army. 2 King 19 one hundred foureſcore and fiue thouſand ſlaine in one night without an enemy:
<note place="margin">2 <hi>King.</hi> 19 35.</note> 
               <hi>Cautior Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplo Tu.</hi> Each one take heede that wee doe not repeat this Errour, this impious Preſumption; as I feare, too many of this Kingdome doe, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lying too much vpon Earthly Force; miſattribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting our long peace and ſafety to the populouſnes of this Nation, and admired Shipping of our Moa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted-Iſland: God is not in all their thoughts, like the proud <hi>Emperour</hi> that cut off the heads of all the Gods in Roome,
<note place="margin">Nero.</note> and cauſed the Image of his owne be ſet vpon them, Wee ſacrifice to our own ſword and ſpeare, when Tis the Right-hand of the Lord that bringeth mighty things to paſſe: Theſe (I confeſſe, ſhipping and munition) are meanes and inſtruments, but unleſſe from God, whence are they all? and, without his aſſiſtance, may ſoone againe (as often heeretofore) become <hi>Ventorum Ludibrium,</hi> a prey to Tyrants, the ſport and rattles of the winde and waves; I, may ſhare in that doome of <hi>Tyre</hi> againſt the ſhips of <hi>Tarſhiſh
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:1845:14"/>Iſa.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſai.</hi> 23 14.</note> 23. <hi>Bee ſtill yee that dwell in the Iſles, who are called the ſtrength of the Sea, whoſe Merchants are as Princes: howle yee ſhips of Tarſhiſh, for your ſtrength is laid waſte.</hi> You can remember, we have been driven to that of <hi>David,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 60.10.</note> Thou, O God, wenteſt not forth with our Armies,</hi> till we came to his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment there,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>verſ.</hi> 11.</note> 
               <hi>vaine is the help of man.</hi> v. 11. God will have the glory of our wellfare, and fit he ſhould, ſince hee is the authour of it, who elſe live heer in a ſhop of angry Meteors, violent Elements, each of which (as well as forraigne enemies) would ſoone deſtroy us, were not Hee our Lord Protectour: how often therefore and how juſtly does <hi>David</hi> call Him Rocke and Refuge, Strength and Tower, Caſtle and Fortreſſe: Conclude wee then with him.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4.8.</note> 
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4. <hi>Thou Lord only makeſt us to dwell in ſafety, who have elſe no continuing City heer, no City of ſafety.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſt of all,
<note place="margin">A City an em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blem of reſt. Man <hi>no conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing City. Ioſh.</hi> 21.</note> a City is an Hieroglyphick of reſt, and therefore in the 21. chapter of <hi>Ioſhua</hi> tis ſaid, <hi>God gave his people Citles which they builded not, and reſt round about them:</hi> nay, eternall reſt it ſelfe borrowes an expreſſion from the name of City. Tis called <hi>The new Ieruſalem,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.21.</note> the City of the living God.</hi> But man is no Citizen of this, as tis a repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentative of reſt, his life a giddy-wheele; the Orbs, the Clouds, the Windes, the Rivers not ſo full of motion (his Bodies reſtleſneſſe you ſaw before) I ſpeake now of the travells of his minde, that buſie Spirit hurried through thouſands of the worlds diſtractions, which yet, if beſt imployed, is ſubject to bee tyred: even Reading is a wearineſſe (ſaies the wiſe Man) and ther's no end of many bookes (unleſſe an
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ</hi> 12.12.</note>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:1845:14"/>end of their Authour.) But if this Mill grinde empty, have not the minde good things to worke on, and how does it ſet it ſelfe on fire! on fire of hell, by ſinnefull and cupidinous Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volutions! what miſchiefe leaves it unima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined on the Bed, unpractiſ'd up! how full of all contemplative uncleaneſſe! even to the making up that ſinnefull Climax. <hi>Geneſis</hi> 6.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.5.</note> The Heart of Man, the Thoughts of the Heart, and Imaginations of the Thoughts, are all evill, evill onely and continually no reſt from ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: and thence how reſtleſſe,
<note place="margin">Conſcientia ſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num aut ſlagel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum.</note> (thinke you) is the guilty Conſcience, (onely in this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular like to God, that it never ſlumbers nor ſleepes) the clamour of this ſhrew, deading the noyſe of Ravens or of Thunder; not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly audible to us waking, but interrupting of our beſt repoſe: <hi>Job</hi> 7.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 7.13.</note> 
               <hi>when I ſay my Bed ſhall comfort mee, and my Couch ſhall give mee reſt, then thou frighteſt mee with Dreames, and terrifiest me with viſions:</hi> Enough to make one wiſh with <hi>David,</hi> one's owne Metamorphoſis, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 55. <hi>Quis dabit Pennas Columbinas!
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55.6.</note> Oh that I had wings like a Dove! for then would I fly away and be at reſt:</hi> at reſt from the diſtracting cares that follow this vaine worlds affaires! at reſt from the impetuous ſolicits of the fleſh! at reſt from the importunate temptations of the Devill! at reſt from the refractory impieties of wicked compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny! all which make every honeſt <hi>David</hi> ſigh out heer, <hi>Vae mihi miſero, Pſa.</hi> 120. <hi>Woe is mee,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 120.5.</note> that I am conſtrained to dwell in Meſeck, &amp;c.</hi> Thus is our life a toſſed Arke, tumultuous without, ſicke with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; and the poore ſoule (like <hi>Noahs</hi> reſtleſſe Dove
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:1845:15"/>can finde no ground to fixe on,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Inquietum eſt cor meum donec requieſcat in te. Reu.</hi> 14.13. <hi>Iob.</hi> 14 2.</note> till ſhee returne from whence ſhee flew at firſt; and then indeed ſhee reſts, reſts from her labours, ſo ſaies the Spirit, <hi>Revel.</hi> 14. but heere, hath no <hi>continuing City,</hi> no <hi>City</hi> of reſt. <hi>Iob</hi> ſummes up all my par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, chap. 14. v. 2. and the totall is, <hi>Man borne of a Woman, is but of few daies and many trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, hee commeth up like a Flower and is cut downe, he never continueth in one ſtay</hi> (ther's the Text in Paraphraſe) hath <hi>no continuing City.</hi> And having thus demoliſhed this earthly City, how can wee now chooſe but (with
<note n="*" place="margin">Livius.</note> 
               <hi>Metellus</hi> ſacking <hi>Siracuſe</hi>) lament the tranſient vanity thereof, and bewaile our ſtrong deſires of ſo weake an object, as <hi>no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing City.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But leaſt a too long diſcourſe heere contradict my <hi>Theſis,</hi> and prove it a continuing City, I paſſe the Plainteifs and their wants, to take a glance, by way of application, on their place of ſtreights, the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Text.</note> where wee are ſo indigent, and thats <hi>Hic,</hi> Heere.</p>
            <p>Indeed there is a place, where the woman is <hi>cloathed with the Sunne,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Reu.</hi> 12.</note> and the Moone under her feet</hi> (.i.) where the Church and every member of it, is roab'd with glory, and farre above the reach of any mutability;
<note place="margin">Bernard.</note> but as Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaies, <hi>ſurrexit, non eſt hîc,</hi> this is in the City thats above, it is not heere: This place is the Moones chiefe Regiment,
<note place="margin">The <hi>Vbi</hi> where we are ſtreight<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned.</note> her very exchange (as it were) to vent all her varieties <hi>(conſtat genitum nihil,)</hi> ſave alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration nothing continues heer.</p>
            <p>Earth (you ſee) is the leaſt of Elements, and to the Heavens, no more than is a ſingle Atome to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:1845:15"/>the Sunne; an infinite ſubſtance then (ſuch as the ſoule of man is) needs muſt bee ſtreightned heere: this little circle can never fill the hearts vaſt Trian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle, thât nothing but the Trinity: vaine therfore the continuing heere: This againe is the loweſt, and moſt dreggiſh Element, the ſinke of all, and ſo <hi>Cladium Officina,</hi> the ſhop of dangers and diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and they both ſo deſtructive, that no continuing heer, <hi>ſtatio malefida carinis.</hi> Tis the valley of the world, Earth, the valley of teares, teares indeed,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> where we enter life with cryes, continuing with ſighes, and going out with groanes: This is our muſicke heere! heere, where mirth is but appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, griefe is reall: where wee eate the bread of carefulneſſe,
<note place="margin">Panis noster lapidoſus.</note> mingling our drinke with weeping, all our actions with ſinning, this is our diet heere! heere where wee onely taſte of joy, but glut in ſorrow; we walke in happineſſe, but journey in calamity, this is our travell heer! heer, where riches are but thornes, honours but pinna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, and pleaſures
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Habet omnis hoc voluptas, ſtimulis a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>git feuentes, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piumque par va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantum, &amp;c. Boet. de Con. Dan</hi> 232.</note> Bees that leave more ſting than hony: theſe are our treaſures heer! ſo that the world (you ſee) with all its pompe, makes but up a <hi>Nebuchadnezars</hi> Image, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2. though the head bee gold, the breaſt of ſilver, belly braſſe, and legges of yron, yet are the feet of clay: let one be honourable, another rich, a third beaute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, a fourth nere ſo vigorous, yet are the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of them all but clay, and a ſmall ſtone from out the ſling of death does breake and liken them to duſt: and this the end of all things heere.</p>
            <p>Now, mee thinkes, by this time, we ſhould be all of holy <hi>Monicas</hi> minde, S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Austins</hi> pious
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:1845:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>Mother, who (as he tells us) having thus diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed over the frailty of the world together, melted into this expreſſion:
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Quantum ad me attinet, nullâ re jam delector in hac vitâ. Quid hîc facio? lib. confeſſ. c.</hi> 10. <hi>Iob.</hi> 14 14.</note> For mine owne part (ſaies ſhe) I am now delighted with nothing in this world, and what doe I longer heer but practiſe <hi>Iobs</hi> attendance? So after all this colloquie of ours (anatomizing the vaine world) what can you finde heere worthy your affections? not worthy your diſdaine? <hi>Quid hic facimus?</hi> then what do we do heer, heer in our unſatisfi'd deſires? our eager proſequutions? treaſuring for the Moath and Theefe, like Spiders, ſpending our bowels to catch Flyes,
<note place="margin">Menott.</note> and (as <hi>Menott</hi> ſaies of wily Hunters) loſing an Horſe of price in purſuit of an Hare worth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; heer being neither City of Strength (you ſee) nor City of Unity, nor City of Reſt, nor City of Safety: <hi>no continuing City;</hi> what doe wee then heere,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ixion. Alexanders</hi> queſtion.</note> graſping of a Cloud for <hi>Iuno!</hi> Twas a que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion once debated in the Court of <hi>Alexander,</hi> what was the greateſt thing in the world? and having many about him of all Sciences, a Geogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher anſwers him, the Mount <hi>Olympus,</hi> that hill indeed being ſo vaſt and high, as frequently is took for Heaven it ſelfe: an Aſtronomer, hee anſwered twas the Sun, that world of light ſo
<note n="*" place="margin">The Sun big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger than the earth 166. times according to <hi>Euſtach.</hi> and others. <hi>Luk.</hi> 14 33.</note> many times bigger than the earth; a Paraſite tells him his own victory: but an honeſt Moraliſt that ſtood by, affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the greateſt thing in the world, to be an heart that could contemne the greateſt: well ſaid Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher, anſwered as though he had heard Chriſt himſelfe preach on that fourteenth of <hi>Luke: Qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque non reliquerit omnia, who ſo forſakes not all (in competition <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> mee) is not worthy of mee, nor of Heaven,</hi> a paire of imitable examples, one of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:1845:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>them, a Heathen, and ſhall Chriſtians come behind ſuch, in contemning of the world and greateſt things of it, (then let us even change names with them) but let our ſoules aſpire with <hi>Monica's</hi> (that glory of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſex and coppy of the other) <hi>Quid hic facio?</hi> what doe wee doe heer? like <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>via,</hi> thirſt for better waters <hi>Pſal.</hi> 42.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 42.1.</note> and yet as twas with <hi>Monica, unum erat, &amp;c.</hi> one thing there was that made that female Saint deſire a little longer continuance heer; ſc. her ſonnes converſion, and to ſee him baptized a Chriſtian. So one thing muſt our ſoule deſire of God, that wee may live to ſee that chriſtened, baptized in the teares of penitence; and then <hi>quid hic facio,</hi> away to our <hi>continuing City;</hi> what doe ſuch Eagles heer, when as their Carkeiſe is in Heaven? indeed what doe wee ſo long, loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king on this Terrene-globe? whoſe Zones are all intemperate (freezing charity, or ſcorching envy, avaritious drought, or riotous profuſeneſſe) whoſe paralels are equall, cares and feares: whoſe Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference is vanity, and Center is corruption.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Respicite jam Coeli Spatium &amp; definite ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quando vilia mirari.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Boet. l.</hi> 2. <hi>Con.</hi>
               </note> Hearke how the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher calls us off, behold now the beauteous frame of Heaven, and deſiſt at length to admire baſe earthly things:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tranſitus in</hi> 2. <hi>gen.</hi>
               </note> let the bodies figure be the ſoules tutour, and a <hi>ſurſum oculi</hi> teach <hi>ſurſum corda,</hi> an elevated eye an upright heart: the heart to ſeeke that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>Continuing City,</hi> the eye <hi>to looke for one to come:</hi> and thats the ſecond Generall, the Coeleſtiall Sphoere of this ſame Chriſtian-Map. <hi>Wee looke for one to come.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:1845:17"/>
            <p>And here the Chriſtian and the Heathen Part, Who haue all this while gone along together in the <hi>Non habemus.</hi> They likewiſe vndauntedly apprehending their mortality, and ſuch as dare to haſten it.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mors malorum remedium, miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riarum finis.</hi> Cicero.</note> 
               <hi>Vitae prodigioſè prodigi,</hi> deſperate vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrifts of their Blood, onely to period their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries; yet ſome of Them in generall Notions dreamt of the Soules Immortality: <hi>huc Ethnici,</hi> ſaies <hi>Lorinus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In locum.</note> thus farre ſhined the dim Light of Nature, here were their <hi>Herculean Pillars;</hi> But with any Indeauour of good works to ſeeke, or With the Eye of Faith to looke for one to Come; This is a regenerate Mans <hi>Plus <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ltra: Haec Fides, haec Spes eſt Chriſtiana,</hi> This only is a Chriſtians Hope, the <hi>Child</hi> of propagatiue Faith: what a ſtrange Cloſe was that of dying <hi>Adrian. Animula <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>agula blandula,
<note place="margin">Auſon Epigram.</note> Hospes Comeſque Corporis, Quae nunc abibis in Loca.</hi> Little wandring merry Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, Body's Gueſt, and Wont to cheere it, what Place ſhalt Thou now inherit! &amp;c. alas!
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Virtutes Eth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicorum ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt ad ornan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum vitam hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manam, non ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinere vit aeter.</hi> Aug.</note> 
               <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens</hi> find but diminitiue Comfort at their death, treading thoſe vnknowne Paths with vnprepared Feet, going from one Darknes to another, oh! How may wee ever bleſſe God for our vocation, our double Light of Grace and Knowledge, when the Moſt Learned of them goe Hence with a <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcio quo Vado:</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">As it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported of <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle, Ens entium miſerere mei,</hi> &amp;c <hi>Iob</hi> 19.25.</note> I know not whither I go: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the meaneſt Chriſtian with a <hi>Iobs</hi> Faith Exul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth. <hi>Scio quod Redemptor Vivit.</hi> I know that my Redeemer liveth, and therefore <hi>Egredere Anima.</hi> Goe forth my cheerfull Soule,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hilarions</hi> dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſpeech.</note> and feare not now to goe to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> whom Thou ſo long haſt Seru'd: Yet is't not mine here, rigorouſly to determine all thoſe Loſt, whoſe Exact Virtues, ſo out-Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rald
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:1845:17"/>
               <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> Wee cannot Limit Mercy, <hi>God</hi> Loves it aboue <hi>Sacrifice, Math</hi> 9.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 9.23.</note> and our iuſt <hi>Lord</hi> requires but according vnto what he gives. <hi>Luke the</hi> 12.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 12.48. The fearefull ſtate of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens.</note> though indeed the Heathen-people that know not <hi>God,</hi> in reſpect at leaſt of outward Calling, are not within the Pale of the Meſſiahs Deare; and the Law ſo written in their hearts; I Feare, that Suppreſſing thoſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, inhae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Evidences of Nature (which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> Cals withhoulding of the Trueth in Vnrighteouſnes,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.18. and from thence to the end.</note> 
               <hi>Rom</hi> 1.) does <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> render them inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſable (as the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> argues ſtrongly in that fore-cited Chapter) <hi>Nullum aliud Nomen: Acts.</hi> 4.12. there being no other Name &amp;c. but not to make our ſelves inexcuſable by iudging an other, <hi>Sub Iudice lis ſit,</hi> This wee leave to the great Iudge of All, Revealed Things to vs; albeit we ſay not what becomes of Them, Yet to our gratefull Comfort <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> wee know (ſaith hee) that when this Earthly Tabernacle of ours ſhall bee diſſolved, wee have a Building not made with Hands &amp;c. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1.</note> 
               <hi>Futuram Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctamus, we looke for One to Come:</hi> And yet our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence is too weake to goe alone, It muſt be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with Diligence, wee may not Think to enioy that <hi>City</hi> to Come Only with Looking For. They would not be ſo Few then that are Choſen. Matth. 20.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 20.16.</note> All are Baalamites and deſire the Death of the Righteous, but vainely, vnles They live the Life of <hi>Him;</hi> Tis ſtolid to Expect an End without the Meanes. To looke for this ſame City and not ſeeke it: indeed this <hi>Expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> is too ſlacke a Word, <hi>Inquirimus</hi> ſaies <hi>Beza</hi> and the Vulgar, better: and the Originall is neither
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:1845:18"/>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> nor <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that any Lazie Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence ſhould thinke to gaine it, as <hi>God</hi> Knowes that's all the Evidence Many have to ſhew for it, I hope Well; but for all this Hope (if no endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour els) the Heart may breake: No, nor is it Faith Can looke for't vnles operative (wee Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronize not <hi>Solifidianiſme,</hi> Our Adverſaries ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall vs) our Faith Cries out like <hi>Rachel,</hi> give me Children,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 2.20.</note> or I die: <hi>Iames</hi> 2. But ſuch a Faith as workes by Love, maketh our Hope infallible, of Finding what wee ſeeke <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> wee ſeeke one to Come.</p>
            <p>Seeke then, is a word of Labour: bidding vs with the Apoſtle,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil</hi> 2 12.</note> Worke out our Salvation, <hi>Phil</hi> 2.12. worke, T'is not a Feaſt or a Feather-Bedd will bring a Man to Heaven, <hi>non ſic itur ad aſtra.</hi> Our <hi>IehoVah</hi> will not as the Poets <hi>Iove</hi> did into <hi>Danaes</hi> Lap,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Verbum ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randi.</hi>
               </note> rajne downe this goulden Purchaſe into our Boſomes: no, no Drones ſhall Ever taſte the Hony of that Hive but thoſe induſtrous Bees alone that ſeeke it; a Sharpe reproofe for I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dlenes, that Gate of all Impieties, a Whipp of Scorpions for the Sluggards Back. <hi>Pro.</hi> 6. who like the Spouſe,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 6.10.</note> 
               <hi>in Lectulo quaeſivit Quem amavit,</hi> Seekes no farther then his Pillow: but ſhee found not her Beloved there;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 3.1.</note> as little They ſtretching on their bedds of Ivory, e're find his Benefits whoſe Bedd was but a Manger; but Ruine ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 6.15.</note> for their not ſeeking, finds out Them. <hi>Pro.</hi> 6.15. Idlenes you know, it was denominated thoſe Virgins fooliſh, and excluded them both the Chamber, and the knowledge of the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groome,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.10.</note> 
               <hi>Matth.</hi> 25. Thus ſlothfull perſons (like Arrowes from a feeble bow) fall ſhort of what
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:1845:18"/>they ayme at, and with <hi>Eſau</hi> come too late to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>une the bleſſing <hi>Gen.</hi> 27.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 27 30.</note> Diligence invites ableſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing; you ſee, <hi>Moſes</hi> keeping watch over his flock by night, is grac'd with viſions, <hi>Exod.</hi> 3.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 3.4.</note> a ſight of Him whoſe viſion is beatificall, and <hi>Saul</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king his Fathers Aſſes finds a kingdome 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 9.
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam</hi> 9 20.</note> and <hi>David</hi> is taken from following the Ewes great with young, and made the great Shepheard of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.71. Diligence invites a Bleſſing.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalme</hi> 78.71. Diligence in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites a bleſſing; Idlenes temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</note> whereas on the contrary, Idleneſſe allures tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, tempts the Tempter; while <hi>David</hi> exerciſed himſelfe in Gods Law day and night, all went well with him, hee feard not what either man or Satan could doe to him; but when once hee aſcends his wanton proſpects, and looſens the reines unto his idler ſenſes; the Devill ſoone changes his title, and makes him a man after his owne Heart, wraps him in a double ſnare of Murder and Adultery; and after theſe, how juſtly hee complaines,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalme</hi> 6.7.</note> 
               <hi>mine eyes are dimme,</hi> when ther's ſuch a pearle in one and the tother blood-ſhod! So aske but the Poet's <hi>Egistus</hi> and many of his Diſciples in theſe times,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Quaeritur Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gillus quarè ſit factus adulter? i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> promptu cauſa eſt, &amp;c.</hi> Ovid.</note> what fills their name and bones with early rottenneſſe? and ſhame (if any left) will ſoone write the cauſe upon each forehead, <hi>Deſidioſus cram:</hi> indeed, it is the ſitting bird that is the Fow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers ayme, the envious man ſowes his tares while the Husbandman ſleepes; and hell it ſelfe is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding to Idleneſſe, not onely for company, but for a deſcription, being called <hi>Stagnum</hi> (.i.) a Lake,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rou</hi> 21 8.</note> a ſtanding water: ther's an old Apologue how once the Elements contended for priority; the Fire moſt active got ſupremacy, the Agil-Aire wonne the next Regions, the ambitious
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:1845:19"/>waters flow to overtake them,
<note place="margin">An Apologue of the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note> while drowſie Earth ſat ſtill the while, and therefore is ere ſince diſgraced with the loweſt roome; no ſinne ſo unnaturall, as Idlenes: in a word, the idle man's the Devils cuſhion, whereon he ſits and takes his eaſe, while the well-buſied heart is <hi>Officina Dei,</hi> the Shop or Worke-houſe of the Almighty: Then <hi>Da vacuae menti quo tencatur opus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ovid.</note> let ever ſome good act or other bee as an Anchor to the floating minde; Sedulity becommeth even our civill callings, but for ſpirituall <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (ſaith th' Ap.) <hi>Give all diligence to make your calling and election ſure:</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pet.</hi> 10.</note> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. Tis <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Wee ſeeke one to come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, becauſe tis neceſſary a ſeeker ſhould have eyes as well as feet, knowledge as well as indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry (leaſt,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam</hi> 4.3.</note> as the perverſe Iewes, you aske and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive not becauſe you aske amiſſe) conſider <hi>modum quaerendi,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Quaerendi mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus.</note> the manner how to ſeeke: and that is <hi>Renefaciendo &amp; Patiendo,</hi> by dooing good, and ſuffering evill: Doing good, <hi>Facere est Naturae ſed benefaccre eſt opus gratiae.</hi> To bee active is the worke of Nature, but to doe well is an effect of Grace, and cauſe of proſperous reward, as holy <hi>Moſes</hi> intimates to Iſrael.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.18.</note> 
               <hi>Deut.</hi> 6. <hi>Doe yee that which is good in the ſight of the Lord that you may proſper:</hi> Do you that which is good, and that you may do chiefly with theſe two inſtrument,
<note place="margin">The two chief inſtruments of doing good.</note> 
               <hi>Linguâ precante &amp; Manu ſuccurrente:</hi> by a praying tongue and a relieving hand: Charity and Prayer are the ſwifteſt wings, on which the ſoule can mount to Heaven.</p>
            <p>Firſt,
<note place="margin">Prayer.</note> Prayer is the Iewell of Gods eare, the Dialogue twixt Heaven and Earth, the Tongue
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:1845:19"/>of Angells, the Soules Embaſſadour with God, which never, with a faithfull hand, knockt at Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven-gates and was ſent empty away; what though not preſently heard, tis but to double our importunity? what though not ſtraight way granted, tis but to glorifie our patience? yet ſometimes (I confeſſe) our Prayers like exhala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions drawne up heer, may fall elſewhere in fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſhowers, may light on our poſterity: But fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent prayer never goes un-crownd, <hi>ad ſanita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>em ſi non ad voluntatem,</hi> ſtill heard in a proportion to our well-fare, though not alwaies anſwered accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our wills: Prayer is the ſole Phoenix of the Graces, from out the Aſhes of whoſe ſpicie Neſt, revives a Bird of Paradice; This can make an <hi>Arabia petroſa</hi> as happy as her other Siſter, for ſtony hearts can give us hearts of fleſh. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 11.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezech.</hi> 11 19.</note> There is a kinde of an omnipotence in prayer, it locks and opens Heaven
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>atio Clavis Caeli. Auguſt.</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 18. <hi>c.</hi> 5 7. 2 <hi>King.</hi> 4 33.</note> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 18. renewes ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety twixt parted ſoules and bodies, blowes downe the walls of Ierico, ſtaies the Sunne makes fire deſcend; what cannot it not? <hi>vincit invinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilem,</hi> it holdeth that hand which holdeth all the world, from ſtriking a very <hi>Sodome,</hi> God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe can doe nothing till praying <hi>Lot</hi> is gone. <hi>Gen.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen</hi> 19 22.</note> 19. And tis remarkable in that Dialogue 'twixt God and <hi>Abraham, Gen.</hi> 18.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen</hi> 18.</note> how God there deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted not from granting, till <hi>Abraham</hi> firſt left off petitioning: and therfore (as the Apoſtle wiſhes) <hi>Pray continually,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, (.i.)
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5 17.</note> either <hi>(ſtatis tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poribus)</hi> at conſtant times of publick and retird de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions: or elſe continually, ſc. <hi>per verba aut o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pera,</hi> by good words or workes; for indeed no circumſtances can exclude prayer, and beſides
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:1845:20"/>
               <hi>Quaevis bona actio quaedam oratio,</hi> every good action is a kind of ſupplication: Seeke therefore by do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good, and that firſt by Prayer.</p>
            <p>But becauſe Prayer alone makes a man but like a bird with one wing, or as a boat with one Oare, ſomewhat lame &amp; imperfect to performe this du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.1.</note> according to that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>Let any zeale make what noiſe it will, ſpeak it the tongue of Men and Angels, yet without cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, tis but</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a tinckling, not a wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuned Cymball: Let therfore the praying tongue ſay to the relieving Hand,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ruth</hi> 1.16.</note> as <hi>Ruth</hi> to <hi>Naomi,</hi> whether thou goeſt I will goe, and where thou dwelleſt I will dwell. Let Charity, I ſay, and Prayer like linckes of a golden chaine, depend on one another, <hi>ut quae non proſunt ſingula,</hi> though like two gloves, one loſt the tother but of little uſe; yet both together make themſelves compleate: For God (like <hi>Iſaak Gen.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 27.</note> 27.) will feele the hands as well as heare the voyce of whom hee bleſſeth; <hi>Pliny</hi> tells us of the Eagle,
<note place="margin">Plin. nat. Hiſt.</note> that ſhee knowes her young ones by their eyes, their perſpicacy, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they can out-face the Sunne ſhee rejects them as a baſtard-brood: but God knowes his children by their hands, their liberality: and whom he finds (like <hi>Ieroboam</hi>) withered-handed cloſe-fiſted, he counts them but degenerate ſons, and will diſinherit them of his heavenly kingdom, yet will give them a portion,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 11.1.</note> I tremble to ſay where: caſt then thy bread upon the waters (.i.) relieve the needy, whoſe multitude and weakneſſe tearmes them ſo, and after many dayes (for Heaven will never forget it) thou ſhalt finde it: I, flowing to thee like rich merchandize with bleſt increaſe:
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:1845:20"/>
               <hi>Miſcris ſuppreſſa levate Pectora:</hi> each one that that craves an almes, is an arme ſtretcht out from God, who hath another hand as ready to reward, as that was to receive (tis <hi>Salomons</hi>) <hi>who ſo hath mercy on the poore lendeth to the Lord,</hi> &amp; indeed, but lendeth, to the beſt advantage, for the Lord will recompence him, <hi>Pro.</hi> 19. God puts us not to the expence of any coſtly ſacrifices (ſhould he,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 19 17.</note> how coldly would his altars lye!) the calves of our lips and offerings of our hands are now all he challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth, and therfore to do good, and to diſtribute for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get not, theſe are the pleaſing ſacrifices. Part with ſome of that which long you cannot keep,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Quas dederis ſolas ſemper ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bebis opes. Luk.</hi> 16.9.</note> to gaine that which you can never looſe: <hi>make you friends of that unrighteous mammon, Lu.</hi> 16. <hi>Euthimius tels us</hi> God hath given men riches <hi>non tanquam Dominis ſed diſpenſatoribus,</hi> not as unto treaſurers, but ſtew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards, imitate then that wiſe one in the Goſpel, for to every one it ſhal be one day ſaid, <hi>redde rationem,</hi> and beleeve it, none ſhal make a better reckoning at the laſt great Audit, than the charitable man <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>love covereth a multitude of ſins,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4 8.</note> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4. and this indeed the Iudg himſelf atteſtates <hi>Mat.</hi> 25 Chriſt there deſcribing his laſt genral ſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſeems to take notice only of workes of mercy,
<note place="margin">Workes of mercy onely inquired of at the day of Iudgement. <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.30.</note> thers no talke of your frugallity your temperance, you dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, or other virtues; but feeding, clothing, viſiting, miniſtring: theſe Chriſt names, &amp; takes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his own account, <hi>mihi feciſtis, you have done it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me,</hi> and therefore repaies them with eternal hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines, <hi>venite benedicti, Come you bleſſed,</hi> &amp;c. Charity is <hi>via ad regnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſi non cauſa regnandi,</hi> the way unto the city that we ſeek, tho not the worth of it. ſeek ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by doing good, &amp; that <hi>linguâ precante et manu
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:1845:21"/>ſuccurrente</hi> by Charity and Prayer: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Text.</p>
            <p>It followes next <hi>Patiendo,</hi> how by ſuffering evill we ought to ſeeke: by ſuffering, For there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto are we called (ſaith th' Ap.)
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2 21.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt alſo ſuffered for us leaving us an example, that wee ſhould follow his ſteps.</hi> And two waies likewiſe muſt we ſuffer, ſc. <hi>Suſtinendo &amp; Abſtinendo:</hi> by bearing and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing in which two things (ſaies <hi>Epictetus</hi>) the ſumme of all Philoſophy,
<note place="margin">E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ictcti Enchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid.</note> and I may adde (almoſt) of all Chriſtianity conſiſts. Firſt <hi>Abſtinendo,</hi> in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing Intemperance, all luxurious riot and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe:
<note place="margin">Hippocrates.</note> 
               <hi>Mater virtutum. Abſtinentia,</hi> tis both the Mother and the Nurſe of virtues, <hi>Hippocrates</hi> his Aphoriſm's true on both ſides, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Diſeaſes both of Body and Mind, for the moſt part, owe their originall to fullneſſe and redundant nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors,
<note place="margin">Patiendi modus.</note> and indeed where Satan tempts one faſting, he tempts a thouſand full, &amp; therfore abſtinence is the beſt cure of both: and oh how well had it been for their poſterity, had but our firſt parents beene acquainted with this virtue in Paradice! then for ought I know they had ſtill beene there, then I'me ſure, had not that ſame one mans meat prov'd ſo all others poyſon: but ever ſince wee matrizare (from that firſt Mother of ours all our vitious long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings) we likewiſe hunger after ſuperfluities and forbidden fruits, not contented with enough are too indulgent to our wanton Genius,
<note place="margin">Abſtinentia frae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iorum.</note> witneſſe the <hi>Plures Crapula quam Gladio,</hi> truer now than ever. Intemperance bringing not onely gray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haires but green yeares with ſorrow to the grave! For how ſoone doe immoderate potions (like much water on a little fire) extinguiſh naturall heat, and as ſoone doe intemperately devoured-Meats
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:1845:21"/>(like much fire, a little water) drink up the radicall moyſture? and heer that Iudaliſme's ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable <hi>ad quid perditio haec?</hi> what need this waſt, waſt of food, waſt of feeders?
<note place="margin">Avidis, avidis Natura parum eſt. Sen. trag.</note> 
               <hi>Naturae parum appetitui nihil ſatis:</hi> a little contents nature, but nothing ſatisfies opinion: <hi>quantos illa morbos,</hi> ſighes <hi>Boeti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>de con.</hi>
               </note> How faſt doth luxury conſume the vitall lampe? ofttimes ſo captivating the body to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſes, that nought can free it but that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that generall remedy of all maladies, an early death: So that the intemperate are of the number of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> wicked ones, <hi>qui vix dimidiabunt dies ſuos,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55.33.</note> that ſcarce live out halfe their daies, and how ever not by the lawes politick, yet by the Divine ſtatutes, each of theſe is <hi>felo de ſe,</hi> by double guilt his owne ſelfe-murderer, be not therefore like that Image of intemperance
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Lucian's</hi> ſcoffe, behold ſhee-<hi>Sardanapalus.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Sardanapalus,</hi> whoſe ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feminate luxury bereft him of his Kingdome, leaſt it bereave you of a better, of the <hi>City that you looke for:</hi> but rather imitate that pattern of abſtinence, the good Emperor <hi>Valentinus,</hi> who of all the conqueſts he had ever won (though many) yet on his death<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, ſaid hee gloried but of one; and being ask'd of which, <hi>Inimicorum inquit, nequiſſimum devici, carnem meam:</hi> the greateſt victory (ſaith hee) that ere I got, was in ſubduing that greateſt enemy mine owne fleſh. I cloſe this with Saint <hi>Peters</hi> dehortation, and in his wooing language. <hi>I beſeech you Brethren abſtaine from fleſhly luſts which fight againſt the ſoule.</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2 12.</note> Seeke <hi>Patiendo</hi> by ſuffering, and that not onely <hi>Absti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nendo,</hi> by forbearing, but likewiſe <hi>Suſtinendo</hi> by bearing evill.</p>
            <p>Bearing evill, I, Affliction is the Coat of a
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:1845:22"/>Chriſtian, and the Croſſe his cognizance <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaid to every one as well as <hi>Constantine,</hi> under this Banner thou ſhalt overcome: are wee not all members of that Head which was crown'd with Thornes! the parts then muſt looke to ſympa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thize together with it,
<note place="margin">Bern.</note> 
               <hi>non per unum foramen caput per aliud membra:</hi> the Head enters not by one paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, the members by an other; but all goe into Heaven at the ſame ſtrait gate: <hi>Porta tribulatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis porta Paradiſi,</hi> the Red Sea is the way to Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan <hi>(hâc itur ad ſuperes) Mount Calvary to Tabor: per varios caſus, per tot diſcrimina. through many tribulations muſt wee enter into that Kingdome,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 14.22.</note> Act.</hi> 14. Affliction (like the Toade) hath a precious pearle in the head, how ever it appeare ugly; no affliction is for the preſent joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, but &amp;c. Adverſity is Gods knife, wherewith hee ſpareth not to lance whom it pleaſeth him to heale, and thoſe (like precious lems) are moſt beautifull after cutting: And albeit our earthly mother, this world, may perhaps for our afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (with <hi>Raohel</hi>) call us <hi>Ben-onies</hi> ſonnes of her ſorrow; yet God our heavenly Father, will one day for our patient ſuffering (with <hi>Iacob</hi>) call us <hi>Beniamins,</hi> ſons of his right hand; You know that of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Auſtin. Deus unicum habuit Filium ſine peccato ſine flagello nullum.</hi> God had never but one Sonne, and that his onely Sonne, without ſinne, but none without affliction; no not <hi>his beloved Sonne in whom he was ſo well pleaſed,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.17.</note> Matth.</hi> 3. <hi>indeed the</hi> rather was hee afflicted for that hee was beloved, ſeeing <hi>He chastneth whom he loveth, and ſcourgeth every ſonne whom hee receiveth, Hebr.</hi> 12. the Rod is the badge of Filiation:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>b</hi> 12.6.</note> and therefore Saint
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:1845:22"/>
               <hi>Auſtin</hi> notes in God, <hi>crudelis miſerecordia,
<note place="margin">Crudelis miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recordia.</note> &amp; miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricors crudelitas,</hi> a cruell mercy and a mercifull cruelty: the firſt when he permits the wicked to proſper in this life, as tis <hi>Iob</hi> 21. the wicked live,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 21.</note> waxe fat, and grow in wealth (ſaith he) but what enſueth: <hi>momento deſcendunt</hi> (a ſad cataſtrophe) in a moment they goe downe to hell, v 13.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 13.</note> a while they flouriſh (ſayes the Pſalmiſt) like a greene Bay Tree, but anon (.i.) when their ſinnes are ripe, they are cut downe like the graſſe, and wither like the green Herbe. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 37.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalme</hi> 37.2,</note> and this indeed is a cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell mercy, no marvell if the Prophet deſired rather Gods mercifull cruelty, <hi>Ier.</hi> 10. Correct mee,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 10.14.</note> O Lord, yet with thy judgement, not in thine anger: The very Heathen could ſay, <hi>Plus hominibus reor adverſam, quam proſperam prodeſſe fortunam:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Boetius.</note> Tis better to have beene afflicted,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 5.17.</note> adverſe fortune more profits man than ſmiling ſtarres: and <hi>Iob</hi> as well as <hi>David</hi> had experienc'd it: Bleſſed is the man (ſaith hee) the man, what man (thinke you) the man thats clad in purple and fares deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly every day? no, thats not hee: is't the man whom the King will honour, with the Ring, and Steed, and royall Roabe? tis not he neither: what then, is't the man that hath caught this world in a purſ-net, and by th'omnipotence of his gold, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands al the felicities that grow in <hi>Salomons</hi> walk <hi>ſub Sole</hi> under the Sun? no, none of theſe, but <hi>beatus a Domino caſtigatus,</hi> bleſsed is the man whom God correcteth. To this purpoſe S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>.
<note place="margin">S. <hi>Auſtins dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue in Soliloq.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Austin</hi> feignes a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference twixt God and himſelfe, God perſonating a Merchant, and himſelfe a chapman. <hi>Vaenale habeo</hi> (ſaies God) I have merchandiſe to ſell. <hi>Quid eſt?</hi> what is it? (ſaies the holy Father) wy <hi>Regnum
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:1845:23"/>Coelorum</hi> (ſaies God) the Kingdome of Heaven: <hi>quo emitur</hi> (ſaies Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi>) whats the price ont? <hi>Paupertate Regnum, afflictione Requies, Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominiâ Gloria:</hi> For poverty (ſaies God) the rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Kingdome; for momentany affliction, eternall reſt, and for reproach, a Crowne of Glory: ſince then our light affliction which is but for a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment bringeth us a more excellent eternal weight of glory,
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.18.</note> 
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. Let us not refuſe the chaſtning of the Lord, but (when he ſends it) patiently ſuffer evill: and thus you have the duty <hi>Seeke, Seeke by doing good,</hi> doe good by Charity and Prayer; and <hi>Seeke</hi> by ſuffering evill, and ſuffer by abſtaining all intemperance, and ſuſtaining all afflictions: ſo run and you ſhall obtaine, thus ſeeke and you ſhall finde <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>the continuing City that wee looke for.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And tis an obiect worthy all this paines: our beſt deſervings undeſerving it: take but a glimpſe on't,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 13.12. The obiect of our ſearch.</note> for we can no more, heer we ſee, as in a glaſſe but darkely 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. Conſider the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> abſtractly as a City, then as a concrete, <hi>One to come:</hi> Firſt, you ſee, tis <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a City, not a Wilderneſſe, as is this world, where we are all in Pilgrimage to the Sepulcher: and behold heer a moſt exact <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 'twixt this ſame and the former City:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>of this City and the former.</hi>
               </note> the worldly one's <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, built but of clay and ſtubble, the worke of mens hands, and thoſe that make them are like unto them, of a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile diſſolution: but this coeleſtiall City is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> made by Him who made the hands, whoſe Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectour is the Almighty, theſe buildings therefore are the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 14.2. 2 Cor. 5.1.</note> 
               <hi>Ioh.</hi> 14. the abiding manſions, whereas thoſe earthly ones are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. but Gourds,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:1845:23"/>but fleeting Tabernacles: you remember tother was a City of Negatives,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> (neither of Strength nor Unity, Reſt nor Safety) this of all good affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, wherein are all Thoſe fixt as in their proper Sphere.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Tis a City of Strength, aske S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Iohn</hi> elſe <hi>Reu.</hi>
               <note place="margin">A City of Strength. <hi>Reu.</hi> 121.</note> 21. the foundation all of Gold, the walls of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damant, and its twelve Gates of Pearle, materialls of the ſtrongeſt;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103 20.</note> yet guarded with innumerable Angels that excell in ſtrength, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103. garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſond with an Army of Martyrs, and govern'd by the Lord of hoaſts, indeed there can want no Strength where dwells omnipotence; heer then were that an opportune deſire, <hi>quis deducet me in Civitatem munitam?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 60.9.</note> who will lead me into this ſtrong city? &amp; that the Text wil if thou follow it.</p>
            <p>This too is a City of Unity,
<note place="margin">A City of Vnity <hi>Charitas virtus viae &amp; patriae.</hi>
               </note> the King of <hi>Salem's</hi> dwelling houſe; thoſe Starres are the embroyde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of Peaces Coate, and the gay-beames of Sun and Moone, but the bright ſmiles of Loue Tryum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant; <hi>Coelum charitatis patria:</hi> Heaven is the place where ſhee was bred (Faith and Hope are low borne virtues to her 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.8.</note> heere they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin and heere they end. But <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> this grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter grace of love &amp; unity (a ſtray indeed on earth) take up their eternall reſt in Heaven, nay there were no Heaven without it: Concord heer, ever flowes and knowes no ebbe: ſpringing from the undivided Trinity, unto the goodly fellowſhip of the Prophets, and communion of all Saints, <hi>qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus lux eadem, Cantio unica.</hi> who ſhining all with the ſame light of glory, breath all the ſame inceſſant Halilujahs: None envying others happineſſe (veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſells all full though of their ſeverall ciſes) None
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:1845:24"/>know either want or emulation. <hi>This Ieruſalem is the City at unity with it ſelfe,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 122.3. A City of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fety.</note> Pſal.</hi> 122.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, tis a City of Safety (you ſee) ſtrengthned beyond all oppoſition, &amp; ſeated above ſhort-armed danger: <hi>Altiſſima venti non perflant,</hi> no angry ſtorme can ſhake the Cedars of this <hi>Libanus,</hi> or blaſt the Aſcenders of this holy Mountaine, heer on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly may wee cry, <hi>Peace, peace,</hi> all ſafety dwelling heer; no enemies being left to interrupt it, Sinne and Sorrow, hell and the grave, all conquerd; <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culcata pedibus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.27.</note> by him who <hi>hath ſubdued al things:</hi> yet were the world let looſe againſt them, Chriſts little flocke need feare no ill; they are in ſuch an hand,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 10.28.</note> as who ſhall take them from him? <hi>Joh.</hi> 10. <hi>Etiamſi fractus illabatur orbis, Impavidos ferient ruinae.</hi> Let the world totter into its firſt Chaos, ruine ſhould threaten them in vaine, <hi>whom God makes dwell in ſafety.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 4.8.</note> Pſalm.</hi> 4. This Canaan's full of ſecure Vines and Fig-trees; the Prophet <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chary</hi> means this City, ſure; when he ſaies <hi>Men ſhal dwell in it, and there ſhall be no more deſtruction, but Ieruſalem ſhall be ſafely inhabited.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Zech.</hi> 14.11. A City of Reſt</note> Zech.</hi> 14.11.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, all theſe ſpeake Heaven a City of reſt, where there is ſuch Strength, and Love, and Safety, needs, muſt there be true ſecurity: I, heaven is the Center of ſoules, as is the Earth of bodies, and onely there they reſt: there indeed being conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation adequate to the Soules capacity (no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſearch no more deſire) wheras heer, one
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>ſacri, &amp; cordis humani figura: quae ſibi mutuo ſolùm ſufficiant. Pſal.</hi> 107 9.</note> cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the heart or other ſtill is empty: <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ulcimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum innitenti, plenitudinem continenti ſufficientiam Poſſidenti coelum praebet:</hi> Heaven ſatisfieth the hungrieſt ſoule with goodneſſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107. And yet this heavenly reſt is not to bee taken (as ſome
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:1845:24"/>impious Spirits) only privatively, as a totall ceſſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from all ſacred buſineſſe (for in that ſenſe, Saints have no reſt in Heaven) never ceaſing to fall down <hi>before the Throne</hi> (ſaith S.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ren.</hi> 4.8:</note> 
               <hi>Iohn</hi>) never ſilencing their ſacred anthems to the King of glory: but as Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy ſaies of the Spheres, ſc. <hi>motus iſte eorvm quies</hi> This holy motion is their endleſſe reſt, reſpect of al moleſt and wonted troubles (which this world ſhowres on them) heer are they ſaid to reſt,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 13.14.</note> and ſo ſaies the Spirit, <hi>Reu.</hi> 13. <hi>they reſt from their labours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now could but divine contemplation tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port you with Saint <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12 2.</note> but ſnatch your ſoules a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>while from out their earthly Tenements, &amp; elevate them to the heaven wee ſpeake of! what glorious objects, not to be revealed, ſhould you there behold? there ſhould you ſee felicity walke hand in hand with eternity; and what this world can never ſhew you, glory attended on by ſafety: <hi>Serenitas ſine nube, Saintas ſine infirmitate,
<note place="margin">Auguſt. de Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitat. Dei.</note> iucunditas ſine moerore, pulchritudo ſine deformitate, Sapientia ſine errore, vita ſine morte.</hi> Ther's light never clouded, health never weakened, pleaſure unmixed with griefe, or beauty with deformity, a Moone with out her ſpots, wiſdome acquainted with no errour, and life beyond the reach of death. <hi>Deum ſine fine videbimus, ſine faſtidio amabimus, ſine defatigatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne laudabimus</hi> (as that Father ſweetly warbles.) there ſhal you ſee th' Eternal eternally, One whom all ſhall love without ſaciety, and unwearied praiſe him continually: there likewiſe ſhould your eares w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> equal happines ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quet themſelves on the true coeleſtial melody (ſweeter than that feigned of the Sphaeres) ſc. of Halilujah-ſinging Saints &amp; Angels: there ſhould you find, <hi>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>curſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> omniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bonoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> as twere
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:1845:25"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:1845:25"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:1845:26"/>an happy Marriage, a conflux of all the Goods uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; ſo that ther's nothing abſent that you could wiſh preſent, nor any thing preſent that you could wiſh abſent,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 87.3.</note> heer then with <hi>David</hi> wee may lye down in wonder <hi>quam glorioſa de te dicta ſunt,</hi> what glorious things are ſpoken of thee thou Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of God! and yet (like as to <hi>Sheba's</hi> Queene) not the one halfe can be told you, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But yet this happines is too much for the preſent <hi>brevior voluptas,</hi> in this life pleaſure is the ſhorter Twinne,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chriſtiani Meſſis in Herba.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and therefore (as an exerciſe of our hope and patience) tis <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>wee looke for one to come:</hi> you ſee the induſtrious Husbandman reaps not preſently, but (with a coſtly confidence) many dayes, weekes and moneths, waites at expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on's gate;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam</hi> 5.</note> ſo muſt wee (ſaies Saint <hi>Iames</hi>) looke for this precious ſeed, and have long patience for it; delay whets our deſires and multiplieth our eſtimation: yet may not violate the rule of pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
<note place="margin">Cicero de conſo.</note> or anticipate the call of Nature; like him, that reading <hi>Plato's</hi> Booke of the ſoules immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, made himſelf away to haſten to it; but ſuch make more haſte than good ſpeed; Chriſtians muſt wrap up <hi>Davids ſitio,</hi> and Saint <hi>Pauls cupio,</hi> in <hi>Iobs expectabo.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 14.14.</note> all the dayes of mine appointed time will I wait till my change commeth, and take the Apoſtles word for't, in due time wee ſhall reap if wee faint not.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 6 9.</note> 
               <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. The Mariner too that man of hopes, the watery-ploughman (you ſee) endures his voyage ere he gaines his fraight (yet,
<note place="margin">Patience.</note> for the moſt part, ſomewhat he receives before hand) but his compleated payment, not till hee makes his ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Porte. So likewiſe in our paſſage to the true Elizium, wee patiently muſt cut through winds
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:1845:26"/>and waves, not looking for our entire wages till our courſe be finiſhed: yet in meane time,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.22.</note> wee are not without that <hi>Arra Spiritus,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt of our hopes, the co-aſſurance of Gods Spirit with ours; I, we have heere Heaven in the bloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, the fruit not till hereafter; heer the harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious feaſt of a good conſcience, which is heaven inchoate, but for the conſummation, <hi>futuram inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimus wee looke for that to come:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>innuit certitudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem &amp; duratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem.</hi>
               </note> This <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>one to come,</hi> intimates heere <hi>certitudinem &amp; durationem,</hi> both the certainty and duration of this ſupernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall City: the certainty, <hi>quia habet rationem promiſſi</hi> becauſe it beares the force of a promiſe, and ſo it is <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> for God hath prepared them a City,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.16.</note> the Saints then ſure enough ſhall have it, ſince Hee hath prepared it, all whoſe promiſes are yea and Amen. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1 20. <hi>Pſalme</hi> 89.3. The certainty of this City.</note> And if his word were not enough, wee have his oath, <hi>Juratus ſum per ſanctitatem,</hi> I have ſworne by my holineſſe (ſaith hee) that I will not faile <hi>David</hi> for ever, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89. <hi>Et vae ſi Deo juranti non credamus,</hi> woe bee to our infidelity, if wee beleeve not the oath which hee ſware in the houſe of his ſervant <hi>David,</hi> that hee would give us, &amp;c. indeed with faithleſſe man, what is to come may ſtill be ſo, but promiſe-kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping is Gods attribute, <hi>David</hi> deſcribes him by it <hi>Pſa.</hi> 77. that keepeth his promiſe for ever.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalme</hi> 77.8.</note> His per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance and his promiſe differ not in eſſence,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.58.</note> if in time, and therefore as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul</hi> exhorts 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. Brethren, bee yee ſteadfaſt, and unmoveable, your Hope being not in vaine in the Lord: <hi>we look for one to come,</hi> and that ſhall come wee looke for: I, and not onely come, but ever ſhall continue; <hi>Futuram</hi> ſpeakes the permanence, that while tis
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:1845:27"/>preſent,
<note place="margin">The duration of it perpetual</note> it ſhall bee ſtill to come: This Future knowes not any preter-perfect-tenſe, yeares ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up dayes, ages ſwallowing yeares, time lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing his <hi>prius</hi> and <hi>poſterius,</hi> nere ſo much paſt, yet nere the leſſe to come: not like our poore joyes heere, <hi>fluunt &amp; praeterfluunt,</hi> no ſooner flow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d to us (almoſt) but ebbing from us: but a continuing City, ſtord with fulneſſe of joy and pleaſures for evermore,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 16.11.</note> 
               <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 16. evermore! more perenni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous than the glyding ſtreame or conſtant Sunne: I, the Sunne may bee one day darkened, and the Moone pay home her borrowed light,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> the fixed Starres may become Planets and wander headlong from their Spheres, whole Nature may ſo forget her office, that heaven and earth may paſſe away <hi>at hae manebunt in aeternum.</hi> but theſe pleaſures (like the right hand they wait on) remaine for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more: and this is our expected City, whoſe inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants, youle ſay (by better title than they of Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus) may bee called Cittizens of no meane City.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 21 39.</note> 
               <hi>Act.</hi> 21. This is the Coeleſtiall Sphere, whoſe Zo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diack is felicity, whoſe Conſtellations are degrees of glory, whoſe Poles, Joy and Eternity. And now you have the paire of Chriſtian Globes, the Map of both worlds ſpread before you, that ſoule w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> travels them well over (this contempt of earth, and ſearch for Heaven) ſhall make a happier voyage
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Drake,</hi> or <hi>Cavendiſh, &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> than thoſe who Ring the Earth, ſhall bee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions of a brighter Sunne: without either coſt or danger may diſcover fortunate Iſles, whence (more then gainefull) bleſt returnes.</p>
            <p>As this experienc'd Heroê hath already: in whom wee finde our Text againe, with a freſh comment on't: his ſoule a faire example of the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:1845:27"/>
               <hi>inquirimus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A Tranſition to the funerall oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion.</note> being fled unto the City that wee ſeeke for, and his body a demonſtration of the <hi>Non ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bemus,</hi> witneſſe this Tenantleſſe houſe of clay, the ſad remainder of our worthy friend and compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhioner M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Henry Chitting,</hi> who is now come hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to take his <hi>ultimum vale</hi> of the world, and tell his good friends that he will meet them in heaven: yet hath he left us ſomewhat elſe behind him, than theſe ſhella of a fledg'd ſoule; ſc. <hi>memoria juſti,</hi> the bleſt memorial of the righteous, which ſhal be had in everlaſting remembrance. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 112. I,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 112.6.</note> now this box of ointment's broken, a ſweet perfume's defu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed through this aſſembly, nay through the whole place of his abode and knowledge: <hi>a good name is like confections of the Apothecary</hi> (faith <hi>Solomon</hi>) <hi>or as muſicke at a banquet of wine.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.</note> His then moſt full of pleaſant Odours in the Noſtrills of God and man, <hi>Vir verè inſignis nec ſilendus nec dicendus ſubitò.</hi> One ſo full of worth and goodnes,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> that Silence may not bury him, Suddenneſſe cannot expreſſe him; I wiſh his bright vertues heer, but ſuch an able Herauld as himſelfe was to emblazon them in their owne co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours; <hi>Nemo Ciceronem niſi Cicero:</hi> for my own part <hi>inopem me copia,</hi> I muſt confeſſe, his ſtore of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit tumultuates my expreſſion, and ſorrow is ſo il a Methodiſt, I ſcarce know where to initiate his En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comium, his juſt commendations,
<note place="margin">I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Epiſt. ad Euſtoch.</note> unleſſe (as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom</hi> of his vertuous <hi>Paula</hi>) I begin with his begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. <hi>Clarus genere Clarior virtute,</hi> he was genteild by bloud and office, yet more enobled by his virtue: as will appeare ſufficiently, if you conſider (with mee) according unto Nature and to Grace, and doubtleſſe all of us may (by the way) finde ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing worth our imitation, his mourning friends matter of conſolation.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:1845:28"/>
            <p>Firſt, Nature (you know) had been no ſtepdame to him, whether you look upon the houſe or the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitant, his body or his ſoule; one of them a good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtructure, a proper manſion for ſo divine a gueſt: as he was not like <hi>Galba,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plutarch in his life.</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.25.</note> who is ſaid to have had a good ſoule in a deformed body; ſo was he not like <hi>Abſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lon,</hi> who had an il ſoule within a comely body. But, <hi>tanto hoſpiti aptum domicilium.</hi> He was a Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond ſet in gold,
<note place="margin">Nature.</note> his body and his mind (like Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of gold in pictures of ſilver) each fitly made for other, and both to praiſe their Maker: but for that part of him which chiefly was himſelfe, his ſoule, ſo eminently ingenious (what with addition of induſtry and education to native diſpoſitions) as long agoe preferd him unto Royal attendance, and a ſtile of honour;
<note place="margin">He was Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Herauld above 20. yeares.</note> 
               <hi>Cheſter</hi> now lamenting her decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Herauld, as we our loving neighbour: we, whoſe every tongue is ſtill his ready Orator, acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging his deportment faire and full of ſweetneſſe compoſed of affection and diſcretion; reſpective of ſuperiours, moſt affable to equalls, ſoft unto in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriours, and lowly towards all:</p>
            <p>But what ſpeake I of Naturalls?
<note place="margin">Grace.</note> Grace was the Altar ſanctified this gold: I, that made his ſoule ſhine like to the Heaven it came from, with many greater and leffer lights: (virtues of all magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes) lights that ſhined before men both in his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer converſation, and his latter viſitation. His con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, to God-ward full of reverence, a practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer of publike as well as private piety: a man after <hi>Davids</hi> heart, that Iov'd the place where Gods ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour dwelleth,
<note place="margin">His Piety.</note> witneſse his diligent frecuenting of this Houſe of prayer; and I were ſomewhat in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratefull (who had the happines to be his friend)
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:1845:28"/>ſhould I not acknowledge him a lover of the Church, her government and Miniſters: and give me leave to wiſh the world fuller of ſuch obedient Spirits.</p>
            <p>For himſelfe, hee no way had defac'd that Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nement where God had houſd his ſoule, nor yet oppreſt the Tenant (.i.) was neither intemperate in body, nor paſſionate in minde; a minde gentle, full of ſoft anſweres, and (as the Apoſtle would have it) <hi>ſlow to anger,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.19.</note> his body a Veſſell of ſobriety not exceſſe;
<note place="margin">His Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</note> not waſhing out his Makers Image with immoderate drinking (that Deluge of the Times) no Sacrifiſer He, to any of thoſe bruitiſh gods, <hi>Bacchus, Venus, Epicurus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom</hi> 13.13.</note> but like a child of light, walking honeſtly as in the day. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. And hee that was ſo pious and ſo temperate could not bee uncompaſſionate, hee that ſo lov'd God whom he had not ſeene, could not but love his brother whom he had: I,
<note place="margin">His Charity.</note> many poore inhabitants of this Pariſh, for his charity, call him bleſſed; and not many weekes are paſt ſince they had a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious taſt on't:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pauper eſt Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare Dei. Are Heb.</hi> 13.16.</note> Hee knew the poore to bee Gods Altar, and therefore to diſtribute forgot not, but offered the well-pleaſing ſacrifice. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.16.</p>
            <p>Thus did a good life approve him (in all the three relations, to God, his Neighbour and himſelfe) an upright Chriſtian;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act</hi> 24.16.</note> one well verſd in Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> endeavour, <hi>Act.</hi> 24. <hi>To keepe in all things a good Conſcience, voyd of offence to God and man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And theſe being the premiſes, with a little Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick you may gheſse at the concluſion,
<note place="margin">Qualis vita Finis ita.</note> 
               <hi>ex veris poſſit nil niſi veraſequi.</hi> None other then a happy end could follow ſuch a well-led life (for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly one is tothers Eccho.) His latter viſitation,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:1845:29"/>was indeed ſhort and ſowre;
<note place="margin">His diſeaſe ſuppoſed an Apoplexie.</note> an acute angry ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lady feeding on his braine, yet for the Senders ſake bid welcome, and entertained with ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved patience, as well deſerved <hi>Iobs</hi> owne commendations: in all this languiſhment he ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned not, nor once <hi>charged God fooliſhly with his lips. Iob.</hi> 2.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 2.10.</note> no, as he was my charge, ſo my comfort to finde him ſtill as full of devotion as affliction, a ready companion of our praiers, making his tongue Gods glory (and his owne as <hi>David</hi> calls it) till ſuch time as the tyranny of his diſeaſe chaind up the faculties of expreſſion,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 57.8.</note> and then reared hands and eyes ſpake louder the elevation of his pious heart, all which petitioned the Churches com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable abſolution, which being adminiſtred, his ſoule (feeling her ſelfe disburdened of a double weight, fleſh and ſinne) ſoone after took her bleſsed flight to Heaven, where is no more Death or ſickneſse, but all teares wipt away: to give your imitation then a Charecter of him,
<note place="margin">The Character of him.</note> in a word. Hee was a zealous Chriſtian, a faithfull Friend, a comfortable Neighbour, a loving Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, a tender Father, an affectionate Brother, a gentle Maſter, a ſweet Companion: in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed living hee was a Common good, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore now a common loſse. Yet this may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort his lamenting friends, that though his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is gone the way of all fleſh, yet his ſoule the way of all the Saints, his Time's extended to eternity, his company (for ſinnefull men) the goodly fellowſhip of the Prophets,
<note place="margin">His exchange.</note> Saints and Angels; and in ſtead heere, of beholding vanity any longer, hee lookes upon the face of God himſelfe, which none can ſee and not bee bleſsed:
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:1845:29"/>thus to him, to dye is gaine,
<note place="margin">Claudite jam rivos.</note> becauſe to live was Chriſt. Then ſhut your ſluces all that lov'd him, and ſeeme not to bowayle his happineſſe, doe not <hi>Reguantem flere</hi> (as Saint <hi>Ierome</hi> forbids <hi>Euſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chium</hi>) doe not you bedew your eyes becauſe God hath wip'd all teares from his,
<note place="margin">Mortui non a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſiſed praemiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi ſancti.</note> 
               <hi>Planctus &amp; ululatus ſint inter ſaeculi homines.</hi> Let ſuch im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate griefe bee among hopeleſse men, that thinke their friends loſt, and gone to a place of weeping.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> And though (in ſuch caſes) wee muſt permit you to bee men, yet forget not to bee Chriſtians; <hi>Doleamus noſtram vicem</hi> (as our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour to the Women) weepe not for him, bleſt ſoule, but for your ſelves, for envie that your ſelves are not ſo happy.
<note place="margin">In Epiſt. ad Euſtoch</note> 
               <hi>Non maereamus qaod ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem amiſſimus, ſed potiùs gratias agamus quod ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buimus imo quod habemus,</hi> (ſweetly Saint <hi>Ierom</hi>) Let us not mourne as for one loſt, rather bee thankefull that wee have had ſo good a patterne, nay, that wee ſtill have him (ſaies the Father) <hi>Deo enim vivunt omnia.</hi> For all ſtill live in God, yea, though they dye, and whomſoever hee thus takes unto himſelfe are ſtill within the Family of the Church. Heare his laſt Farewell now, <hi>Valete omnes, omnes Me, ſuo quiſquis Ordine,
<note place="margin">His Vltimum Vale.</note> ſecuturi. Valete.</hi> Farewell my friends, Brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalls fare you well, that ſhortly (each in his owne order) all muſt follow mee: Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him then firſt in goodneſse, fight the good fight, keepe the Faith, Finiſh ſo your courſe, as hee did, and henceforth is laid up for you (what hee hath now received) a Crowne of Righteouſneſse: Though you goe along with him in the <hi>Non habemus,</hi> having
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:1845:30"/>heere no continuing City: you ſhall alſo accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany him in the <hi>Futuram acquirimus,</hi> the finding one to come: Which God, the Builder and Maker of it, grant us all (in his good time) thorough Ieſus Chriſt. To whom with the Father and the Bleſsed Spirit, bee all honour and Thankeſgivings evermore. Amen.</p>
            <p>—<hi>Tibi deſinet.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="license">
            <p>
               <hi>Perlegi concionem hanc Funebrem cui titulus est</hi> (The Chriſtians Map) <hi>eamque typis mandari permitto.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>SA. BAKER <hi>ex aedib. Londinenſ.</hi>
               </signed>
               <date>
                  <hi>Martii.</hi> 3. 1637.</date>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:1845:30"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
